Guide to the Robert Sabatino Lopez Papers
Yale University Library
Manuscripts and Archives
Robert Sabatino Lopez papers
1932-1987
MS 1459
Lopez, Robert Sabatino, 1910-
14.75 linear feet (31 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, topical files, photographs, and research and writing files which document Robert S. Lopez's career as a professor and scholar of medieval and Renaissance history.
Manuscripts and Archives Sterling Memorial Library 128 Wall Street P.O. Box 208240 New Haven, CT 06520 Web: http://www.library.yale.edu/mssa/ Email: mssa.assist@yale.edu Phone: (203) 432-1735 Fax: (203) 432-7441
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers were the gift of Mrs. Robert S. (Claude) Lopez in 1987. Transferred from the Visual Resources Collection, Yale University (Accession 2009-M-006), 2008.
Biographical Sketch
Robert Sabatino Lopez was born in Genoa, Italy, in 1910. He received a Dottore in Lettere degree from the University of Milan (1932), and a doctorate from the University of Wisconsin (1942). He taught history, literature, and medieval and economic history in Italy between 1933 and 1938, and emigrated to the United States in 1939. Lopez taught at Brooklyn College (1943-1944), Columbia University (1944-1945) and Yale University (1946-1981). Lopez was instrumental in the founding of the Yale University Graduate School Medieval Studies Program, and served as the program's first chairman from 1961-1974. A prolific writer, Lopez's works include The Birth of Europe (1961) and The Commercial Revolution of Europe (1971). He died in 1986.
Biographical History
Robert Sabatino Lopez was born in Genoa, Italy, in 1910. He received a Dottore in Lettere degree from the University of Milan in 1932 and a doctorate from the University of Wisconsin in 1942. He taught history and literature at the Teacher Colleges of Cagliari (1933-1934), Pavia (1934-1935), and Genoa (1935-1936), then medieval and economic history as Assistant Professor at the University of Genoa from 1936 to 1938.
After immigrating to the United States in 1939, Lopez served as a research and teaching assistant at the University of Wisconsin between 1939 and 1942, as a script editor at the Office of War Information (Voice of America) in 1942-1943, and as a foreign news editor at the Columbia Broadcasting System until 1945.
Lopez taught history at Brooklyn College from 1943 to 1944, and at Columbia University from 1944 to 1945, before he was appointed Assistant Professor at Yale University in 1946. He became Associate Professor of History in 1950, Professor in 1955, Durfee Professor in 1961, and Sterling Professor in 1970. He became a Fellow of Calhoun College in 1947, and served in various administrative capacities. Lopez was instrumental in the founding of the Yale University Graduate School Medieval Studies Program, serving as secretary of the Medieval Studies advisory committee from 1956 to 1961, and as the first chairman of the Medieval Studies Program from 1961 to 1974. He retired from the Yale faculty in June of 1981.
He received honorary degrees from Hebrew Union College of Cincinnati, the Université de Montpellier and the Universita di Roma. In June 1985 he was appointed a Fellow of the National Humanities Center in North Carolina. A member of many professional associations, he was President of the Fellows of the Medieval Academy of America and a Fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Science.
Lopez was the author of fourteen books and more than one hundred scholarly papers, including The Birth of Europe (1961), which was translated into seven languages from the original French, and The Commercial Revolution of Europe (1971), which was translated into five languages.
He was married to Claude-Anne Kirschen Lopez, and was the father of two sons, Michael S. Lopez, and Lawrence C. R. Lopez. Robert Sabatino Lopez died July 6, 1986.
Description of the Papers
The Robert Sabatino Lopez Papers consist of correspondence, topical files, and research and writing files which document his career as a professor and scholar of medieval and Renaissance history.
Series I, CORRESPONDENCE, consists of Lopez's correspondence with his students and colleagues, and with representatives of academic institutions, granting agencies, conferences, professional organizations, and publishing companies.
Series II, TOPICAL FILES, consists of correspondence, memoranda, notes, and printed material arranged by topic. Included in the series are academic course files and files relating to Lopez's administrative and teaching activities at Yale University. The published proceedings from a 1987 conference honoring Lopez in Genoa, Italy are in box 16, folder 305.
Series III, RESEARCH AND WRITING FILES, consists of manuscripts and typescripts of some of Lopez's published and unpublished works, as well as notes and printed material relating to his research and writing.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series and one addition: I. Correspondence, 1937-1986. II. Topical Files, 1936-1987. III. Research and Writing Files, 1932-1985.
Access Terms
Lopez, Robert Sabatino, 1910-; Yale University. Dept. of History.; Yale University. Faculty.; Middle Ages--Study and teaching.; Renaissance--Study and teaching.
Collection Contents
- Correspondence, 1937-1986; Series I; 5' linear feet (13 boxes)
  This series contains general correspondence arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent, followed by correspondence between Lopez and his publishers arranged alphabetically by title of publication. The correspondence of publishers of translations of individual works follows that of the original publisher. Folders containing correspondence with Yale University Press and other publishers are at the end of the series.
  - General correspondence
    - A, 1948-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Airaldi, Gabriella, 1973-1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Antonelli, Giovanni, 1947-1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Arnaldi, Gilmo, 1956-1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Astuti, Guido, 1951-1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Ba, 1951-1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Be, 1948-1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bi-Bo, 1937-1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bra-Bu, 1952-1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Bainton, Roland H., 1952-1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Balik, Stanislav, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bark, William C., 1953-1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Bass, George F., 1972-1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bautier, Robert-Henri, 1963-1982 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Bec, Pierre, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Beckman, Gail, 1966-1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Beik, Paul, 1951-1956 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Beltrani, D., 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Berengo, Marino, 1970-1984 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Beyer, Carlyle, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Bickerman, E. J., 1952-1970 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Bischoff, John Paul, 1970-1986 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Bishko, C. Julian, 1964-1984 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Blomquist, Thomas W., 1964-1980 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Bognetti, Gian Piero, 1947-1962 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Bowsky, William M., 1956-1966 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Boyce, Gray C., 1947-1965 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Branca, Vittore, 1954-1983 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Braudel, Fernand, 1949-1984 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Brewster, Kingman, 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Brockunier, Hugh (and Butterfield, Victor D.), 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Brokaw, Miriam R., 1954-1981 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Brombert, Victor, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Bucher, François, 1946-1973 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Buckley, Maria Cristina, 1973-1979 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Burr Family, 1946-1985 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Ca-Cla, 1947-1983 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Clo-Cv, 1939-1982 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Cahen, Claude, 1950-1965 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Callisen, Sterling A., 1951-1953 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Cambon, Glauco, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Cameron, Rondo E., 1957-1981 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Cancellieri, Jean A., 1975-1983 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Cantor, Jean A., 1960-1972 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Castiglione, Salvatore J., 1955-1968 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Chabod, 1952-1958 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Charanis, Peter, 1950-1973 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Chiappelli, Fredi, 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Cipolla, Carlo M., 1946-1979 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Cochrane, Eric, 1951-1980 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Cohen, Sidney L., 1962-1976 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Constable, Giles, 1961-1979 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Cracco Ruggini, Lellia, 1960-1983 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Crozet, René, 1959-1972 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - D, 1951-1985 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Davidson, Eugene, 1947-1957 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - De Francis, John, 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - De Maddalena, Aldo, 1949-1984 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - De Negri, Ossian, 1950-1985 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - de Roover, Raymond, 1942-1970 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Dhondt, Jan, 1946-1972 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Doehaerd, Renée, 1946-1985 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - d'Ormesson, Jean, 1954-1971 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Duby, Georges, 1960-1984 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Dunham, William Huse Jr., 1948-1962 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Dyos, H. J., 1969-1976 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - E, 1950-1981 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Ehrenkreutz, Andrew S., 1955-1964 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Emerson, William R., 1956-1973 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - English, Maurice, 1963-1980 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Ennen, Edith, 1971-1978 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Evans, Austin P., 1947-1959 (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - F, 1947-1984 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Face, Richard, 1958-1978 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Faci, Javier, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - Falco, Mario, 1939-1961 (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Feldman, George J., 1966 (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - Fellner, William J., 1959-1963 (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Finkelstein, Dorothee, 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Finney, Jessica, 1980-1986 (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - Fisher, Wolfram, 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - Foord, Archie, 1955-1958 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Ford, Guy Stanton, 1948-1952 (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Fox, Edward W., 1960-1971 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - Francastel, Pierre, 1956-1961 (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Frances, Enric, 1957-1961 (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Ga-Gi, 1950-1984 (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - Gl-Gu, 1951-1985 (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - Gabrieli, F., 1950-1954 (Box 4, Folder 89)
    - Galasso, 1967-1980 (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - Ganshof, F. L., 1948-1980 (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - Geanakoplos, Deno, 1960-1973 (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - Geary, Patrick J., 1974-1981 (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - Genoa University, 1953-1958 (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - Gerbi, Antonello, 1956-1976 (Box 4, Folder 95)
    - Gilmore, Myron P., 1959-1978 (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Goitein, Shelomo D., 1952-1983 (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - Golob, E.O., 1959, no date (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - Gorla, Gino, 1947-1958 (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - Gouron, André, 1970-1978 (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - Graziosi, Andrea, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - Grierson, Philip, 1951-1959 (Box 5, Folder 102)
    - Guerlac, Henry, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 103)
    - Guggisberg, Hans Rudolf, 1964-1984 (Box 5, Folder 104)
    - Ha-He, 1939-1982 (Box 5, Folder 105)
    - Hi-Hu, 1951-1985 (Box 5, Folder 106)
    - Havighurst, Alfred F., 1956-1960 (Box 5, Folder 107)
    - Heaton, Herbert, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 108)
    - Heers, Jacques, 1950-1971 (Box 5, Folder 109)
    - Henneman, John, 1964-1973 (Box 5, Folder 110)
    - Henriques, Cyril, 1946-1969 (Box 5, Folder 111)
    - Herbert Warren, Eugenia, 1955-1971 (Box 5, Folder 112)
    - Herlihy, David, 1954-1968, 1969-1985 (Box 5, Folder 113-114)
    - Herold, J. Christopher, 1952-1957 (Box 5, Folder 115)
    - Hill, John Hugh, 1958-1966 (Box 5, Folder 116)
    - Hoyt, Robert S., 1962-1964 (Box 5, Folder 117)
    - Hughes, Diane Owen, 1975-1980 (Box 5, Folder 118)
    - I, 1946-1976 (Box 5, Folder 119)
    - Ilardi, Vincent, 1959-1964 (Box 5, Folder 120)
    - J, 1953-1985 (Box 5, Folder 121)
    - Jenks, Stuart, 1974-1985 (Box 5, Folder 122)
    - Jones, Theodore F., 1950-1957 (Box 5, Folder 123)
    - Ka-Ki, 1939-1983 (Box 6, Folder 124)
    - Kl-Ku, 1948-1979 (Box 6, Folder 125)
    - Kaeuper, Richard W., 1972 (Box 6, Folder 126)
    - Karlin, Patricia, 1967-1970 (Box 6, Folder 127)
    - Kedar, Benjamin, 1966-1986 (Box 6, Folder 128)
    - Kellenbenz, H., 1967-1973 (Box 6, Folder 129)
    - Kennedy, John Fitzgerald, 1961-1962 (Box 6, Folder 130)
    - Kitzinger, Ernst, 1955-1971 (Box 6, Folder 131)
    - Koenig, Duane, 1967-1971 (Box 6, Folder 132)
    - Krekic, Barisa, 1967-1985 (Box 6, Folder 133)
    - Krueger, Hilmar, 1947-1955 (Box 6, Folder 134)
    - Kuttner, Stephan, 1947-1973 (Box 6, Folder 135)
    - L, 1946-1984 (Box 6, Folder 136)
    - Labande, Edmond-René, 1957-1976 (Box 6, Folder 137)
    - La Monte, John L., 1946-1947 (Box 6, Folder 138)
    - Landes, David S., 1956-1973 (Box 6, Folder 139)
    - Lane, Frederic C., 1946-1975 (Box 6, Folder 140)
    - Lanzarotto, Ettore, 1953-1969 (Box 6, Folder 141)
    - Lascaris, M., no date (Box 6, Folder 142)
    - Le Goff, Jacques, 1956-1982 (Box 6, Folder 143)
    - Lemerle, Paul, 1958-1982 (Box 6, Folder 144)
    - Lewis, Archie, 1947-1982 (Box 6, Folder 145)
    - Leyerle, John, 1971-1973 (Box 6, Folder 146)
    - Lorch, Maristella, 1972-1976 (Box 7, Folder 147)
    - Luzzatto, Gino, 1938-1962 (Box 7, Folder 148)
    - Lyon, Bryce, 1974-1981 (Box 7, Folder 149)
    - Ma-Mc, 1946-1986 (Box 7, Folder 150)
    - Me-Mu, 1951-1983 (Box 7, Folder 151)
    - Mac Kinney, Loren C., 1951-1960 (Box 7, Folder 152)
    - Malan, Gustavo, 1965-1973 (Box 7, Folder 153)
    - Martines, Lauro, 1963-1979 (Box 7, Folder 154)
    - Martini, Giuseppe, 1964-1971 (Box 7, Folder 155)
    - Mathias, James F., 1943-1973 (Box 7, Folder 156)
    - Mazzaoui, Maureen F., 1971-1980 (Box 7, Folder 157)
    - Melis, Federigo, 1951-1973 (Box 7, Folder 158)
    - Metraux, Guy S., 1952-1969 (Box 7, Folder 159)
    - Miskimin, Harry, 1959-1980 (Box 7, Folder 160)
    - Molho, Anthony, 1968-1986 (Box 7, Folder 161)
    - Mollat, Michel, 1958-1981 (Box 7, Folder 162)
    - Mor, Carlo Guido, 1949-1974 (Box 7, Folder 163)
    - Morghen, Raffaello, 1947-1979 (Box 7, Folder 164)
    - Munro, John H. A., 1961-1975 (Box 7, Folder 165)
    - Musca, Giosué, 1966-1984 (Box 7, Folder 166)
    - N, 1940-1981 (Box 7, Folder 167)
    - Nelson, Benjamin, 1946-1973 (Box 7, Folder 168)
    - O, 1948-1975 (Box 8, Folder 169)
    - Obolensky, Demitri, 1958-1983 (Box 8, Folder 170)
    - Odegaard, Charles E., 1949-1951 (Box 8, Folder 171)
    - Oliveira Marquez, A. H., 1965 (Box 8, Folder 172)
    - Pa-Per, 1947-1980 (Box 8, Folder 173)
    - Pet-Pu, 1947-1979 (Box 8, Folder 174)
    - Parker, William N., 1961-1979 (Box 8, Folder 175)
    - Patzelt, Erna, 1947-1965 (Box 8, Folder 176)
    - Pelikan, Jaroslav, 1967-1982 (Box 8, Folder 177)
    - Pertusi, Augusto, 1967-1973 (Box 8, Folder 178)
    - Peters, Edward M., 1969-1985 (Box 8, Folder 179)
    - Peyre, Henri M., 1953-1979 (Box 8, Folder 180)
    - Picchio, Riccardo, 1971-1985 (Box 8, Folder 181)
    - Pierson, George W., 1956-1969 (Box 8, Folder 182)
    - Pistarino, Geo, 1956-1985 (Box 8, Folder 183)
    - Post, Gaines, 1965-1973 (Box 8, Folder 184)
    - Postan, M. M., 1939-1982 (Box 8, Folder 185)
    - Prawer, Joshua, 1953-1985 (Box 8, Folder 186)
    - Price, Mary P., 1969-1973 (Box 8, Folder 187)
    - Pullin, William A., 1947-1952 (Box 8, Folder 188)
    - Q, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 189)
    - R, 1946-1983 (Box 8, Folder 190)
    - Randall, Dale B. J., 1976-1978 (Box 8, Folder 191)
    - Rau, Virginia, 1955-1973 (Box 9, Folder 192)
    - Raymond, Irving W., 1947-1961 (Box 9, Folder 193)
    - Reichardt, Konstantin, 1959-1972 (Box 9, Folder 194)
    - Revelli, Paolo, 1950-1956 (Box 9, Folder 195)
    - Reyerson, Kathryn L., 1976-1984 (Box 9, Folder 196)
    - Reynolds, Robert Leonard, 1945-1966 (Box 9, Folder 197)
    - Riesenberg, P., 1958-1978 (Box 9, Folder 198)
    - Robinson, Fred, 1976-1980 (Box 9, Folder 199)
    - Ross, J. B., 1959-1966 (Box 9, Folder 200)
    - Rosso-Mazzinghi, Stefano, 1960-1973 (Box 9, Folder 201)
    - Rotelli, Claudio, 1971-1972 (Box 9, Folder 202)
    - Roth, Cecil, 1939-1951 (Box 9, Folder 203)
    - Russel, Josiah C., 1949-1975 (Box 9, Folder 204)
    - Sa-Sc, 1946-1984 (Box 9, Folder 205)
    - Se-Som, 1935-1984 (Box 9, Folder 206)
    - Sor-Sy, 1939-1984 (Box 9, Folder 207)
    - Saéz, Emilio, 1964-1978 (Box 9, Folder 208)
    - Sanchez-Albornoz, Claudio, 1947-1959 (Box 9, Folder 209)
    - Sapori, Armando, 1942-1977 (Box 9, Folder 210)
    - Scaglione, Aldo, 1966-1982 (Box 9, Folder 211)
    - Scelba, Cipriana, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 212)
    - Schapiro, Meyer, 1946-1967 (Box 9, Folder 213)
    - Setton, Kenneth M., 1950-1976 (Box 9, Folder 214)
    - Shafer, Boyd C., 1954-1971 (Box 9, Folder 215)
    - Silk, Edmund T., 1948-1960 (Box 10, Folder 216)
    - Sims, Catherine S., 1959-1960 (Box 10, Folder 217)
    - Strayer, Joseph R., 1947-1978 (Box 10, Folder 218)
    - Szyszman, Simon, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 219)
    - Ta-Top, 1942-1981 (Box 10, Folder 220)
    - Tor-Tu, 1943-1977 (Box 10, Folder 221)
    - Tangheroni, Marco, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 222)
    - Teall, John Leland, 1959-1979 (Box 10, Folder 223)
    - Tenenti, Alberto, 1974-1982 (Box 10, Folder 224)
    - Thompson, S. Harrison, 1951-1959 (Box 10, Folder 225)
    - Thrupp, Sylvia, 1952-1976 (Box 10, Folder 226)
    - Toscanini, Walter, 1939-1967 (Box 10, Folder 227)
    - U, 1947-1977 (Box 10, Folder 228)
    - Udina Martorell, Federico, 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 229)
    - Udovitch, Avrom L., 1963-1983 (Box 10, Folder 230)
    - V, 1947-1980 (Box 10, Folder 231)
    - Venturi, Franco, 1951-1972 (Box 10, Folder 232)
    - Vercauteren, Fernand, 1964-1968 (Box 10, Folder 233)
    - Verlinden, Charles, 1946-1979 (Box 10, Folder 234)
    - Vinay, 1960-1969 (Box 10, Folder 235)
    - Violante, Cinzio, 1954-1985 (Box 10, Folder 236)
    - Virgilio, Agostino, 1954-1971 (Box 10, Folder 237)
    - Vitale, Vito, 1945-1953 (Box 10, Folder 238)
    - Vivarelli, Roberto, 1970-1976 (Box 10, Folder 239)
    - Von Grunebaum, Gustav E., 1951-1963 (Box 10, Folder 240)
    - Vryonis, Speros, 1961-1979 (Box 10, Folder 241)
    - W, 1948-1979 (Box 10, Folder 242)
    - Wallace-Hadrill, M., 1972-1974 (Box 11, Folder 243)
    - West, Louis C., 1954-1959 (Box 11, Folder 244)
    - White, Lynn, 1951-1978 (Box 11, Folder 245)
    - Winter, William L., 1955-1961 (Box 11, Folder 246)
    - Wolff, Philippe, 1949-1977 (Box 11, Folder 247)
    - Wolff, Robert L., 1947-1966 (Box 11, Folder 248)
    - Y, 1954-1975 (Box 11, Folder 249)
    - Yavetz, Zvi, 1968-1985 (Box 11, Folder 250)
    - Z, 1953-1981 (Box 11, Folder 251)
  - Publication correspondence
    - Cambridge Economic History, 1945-1985 (Box 11, Folder 252)
    - Civilizations: Western and World: Little, Brown Co., 1969-1981 (Box 11, Folder 253-255)
    - The Commercial Revolution of the Middle Ages: Prentice Hall, 1964-1977 (Box 11, Folder 256)
    - The Commercial Revolution of the Middle Ages: Cambridge, 1974-1985 (Box 11, Folder 257)
    - The Commercial Revolution of the Middle Ages: Aubier-Montaigne (French translation), 1972-1976 (Box 11, Folder 258)
    - The Commercial Revolution of the Middle Ages: El Abir (Spanish translation), 1976-1981 (Box 12, Folder 259)
    - The Commercial Revolution of the Middle Ages: Einaudi (Italian translation), 1951-1986 (Box 12, Folder 260)
    - "Constantine VII Porphyrogeniyus": Encyclopaedia Britannica, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 261)
    - "Genoa": Encyclopaedia Americana, 1967-1970 (Box 12, Folder 262)
    - History of Mankind: UNESCO, 1967-1968 (Box 12, Folder 263)
    - Medieval Trade in the Mediterranean World: Columbia University Press, 1946-1967 (Box 12, Folder 264)
    - Naissance de l'Europe: Armand Colin, 1953-1965, 1962-1984 (Box 12, Folder 265-266)
    - Naissance de l'Europe: Dent (English translation), 1962-1967 (Box 12, Folder 267)
    - Naissance de l'Europe: Evans (English translation), 1965-1980 (Box 12, Folder 268)
    - Naissance de l'Europe: Einaudi (Italian translation), 1962-1972 (Box 13, Folder 269)
    - Naissance de l'Europe: Cosmos (Portuguese translation), 1964-1965 (Box 13, Folder 270)
    - Of Towns and Trades: The University of Minnesota Press, 1963-1984 (Box 13, Folder 271)
    - Storia delle colonie genovesi nel Mediterraneo: University of Chicago Press, 1972-1976 (Box 13, Folder 272)
    - The Tenth Century: How Dark are the Dark Ages?: Rinehart, 1958-1974 (Box 13, Folder 273)
    - The Three Ages of the Italian Renaissance: University Press of Virginia, 1967-1979 (Box 13, Folder 274)
    - Yale University Press, 1969-1973 (Box 13, Folder 275)
    - Other publishers, 1968-1983 (Box 13, Folder 276)
- Topical Files, 1936-1987; Series II; 1.5' (4 boxes)
  This series contains alphabetically arranged topical files.
  - The Club, 1964-1986 (Box 14, Folder 277)
  - Conference on The Dawn of Banking and the Founding of Western Civilization, 1975-1976 (Box 14, Folder 278)
  - Course files
    - Course reading lists, no date (Box 14, Folder 279)
    - Examinations, 1944-1961 (Box 14, Folder 280-281)
    - History 53a and 53b, no date (Box 14, Folder 282)
    - "The World of the Divine Comedy,", no date (Box 14, Folder 283)
  - Fellowships, 1946-1969 (Box 14, Folder 284)
  - Instituto Internazionale di Storia Economica. "Francesco Datini". Prato, 1968-1972 (Box 14, Folder 285)
  - International Byzantine Congress, 1983-1986 (Box 14, Folder 286)
  - Israel, 1971-1985 (Box 14, Folder 287)
  - Kendall Foundation, 1957-1969, 1966-1974 (Box 14, Folder 288-289)
  - Lectures and conferences, 1964-1968 (Box 14, Folder 290)
  - Lectures and conferences, 1968-1971, 1970-1986 (Box 15, Folder 291-292)
  - Liceo Parini case, 1966 (Box 15, Folder 293)
  - Mediaeval Academy of America, 1946-1964, 1953-1983, 1963-1969, 1967-1974, 1981-1984 (Box 15, Folder 294-298)
  - Medieval cities, no date (Box 15, Folder 299)
  - National Humanities Center, 1984-1985 (Box 15, Folder 300)
  - New England conference, 1974-1975 (Box 15, Folder 301)
  - Personal files
    - Academic appointments, 1942-1969 (Box 15, Folder 302)
    - Awards and honors, 1948-1983 (Box 15, Folder 303)
    - Certificates, letters of introduction, etc., 1936-1964 (Box 16, Folder 304)
  - Printed materials, misc., 1937-1985 (Box 16, Folder 305)
  - Recommendation letters, 1948-1961, 1973-1976, 1979-1986 (Box 16, Folder 306-308)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1971-1973 (Box 16, Folder 309)
  - Society for Italian Historical Studies, 1961-1967, 1965-1984 (Box 16, Folder 310-312)
  - Students' bibliographies and maps, no date (Box 16, Folder 313)
  - Yale administrative files
    - Economic history program, 1961-1972 (Box 16, Folder 314-315)
    - Graduate advisees, 1951-1960 (Box 17, Folder 316)
    - History department appointments, 1965-1967 (Box 17, Folder 317)
    - History department: correspondence, 1964-1968 (Box 17, Folder 318)
    - Italian studies program proposal, 1965-1971 (Box 17, Folder 319)
    - Medieval studies, 1973, 1984 (Box 17, Folder 320)
    - Miscellaneous, 1947-1955, 1977 (Box 17, Folder 321)
    - University Library, 1957-1974 (Box 17, Folder 322)
    - Yale Graduate School administration, 1964-1966 (Box 17, Folder 323)
    - Yale Graduate School: correspondence, 1963-1971 (Box 17, Folder 324)
- Research and Writing Files, 1932-1985; Series III; 1.75' (4 boxes)
  This series contains research and writing files arranged alphabetically under the subheadings Articles and chapters, Lectures, Notebooks, Notes, and Reviews.
  - Articles and chapters
    - "Another Renaissance"; "The Byzantine Silk Industry", no date (Box 18, Folder 325)
    - "Benedetto Zaccaria", 1949-1960, no date (Box 18, Folder 326-327)
    - Cambridge Economic History, 1945-1952 (Box 18, Folder 328)
    - "The Fourteenth Century Crisis", no date (Box 18, Folder 329)
    - Historia Universal, 1979 (Box 18, Folder 330)